Guide to the Student Action With Farmworkers records, 1950-2020, bulk 1992-2016 RL.01128
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Student Action With Farmworkers records
1950-2020
1992-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Student Action with Farmworkers (Organization)
RL.01128
135 Linear Feet 148 boxes
The records of the Durham, N.C. organization Student Action with Farmworkers comprise: administrative and event files; correspondence; reports, articles, and other publications; student project files; outreach and teaching materials; photographs, artwork, and scrapbooks; audio and video recordings; and materials related to labor organizing and protests across the U.S. Hundreds of student-led projects document through interviews, essays, photographs, videos, and other materials the lives of migrant farmworkers and their working conditions, mostly in NC but also in SC. Major themes in the collection include: history, working conditions, and abuses of migrant farmworkers in the U.S.; education and outreach efforts; housing, health, and pesticide safety; leadership development for migrant youth; grassroots theater; labor organizing and boycotts; and service learning. Materials are in English and Spanish. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Collection Arrangement
Collection is arranged in the following series: Administrative Files, SAF Student Projects, Audiovisual Materials, Printed Material, Joan Preiss Papers, and Ephemera and Artifacts. Most series are further divided into subseries.
Historical Note
Adapted from Student Action with Farmworkers website: http://saf-unite.org/
Founded in 1992, Student Action with Farmworkers is a 501(c)3 non-profit organization whose mission is to bring students and farmworkers together to learn about each other's lives, share resources and skills, improve conditions for farmworkers, and build diverse coalitions working for social change. SAF accomplishes its mission by working with farmworkers to address their concerns through documentation of human rights violations, grassroots education and mobilization, leadership development of young people, policy advocacy, and support of labor organizing.
Student Action with Farmworkers (SAF) traces its history to the 1970s when child psychiatrist Dr. Robert Coles and professor Bruce Payne led twelve Duke University students in a summer-long Migrant Project, investigating conditions in NC migrant camps, testifying before the Occupational Safety and Health Administration, and successfully lobbying for the creation of NC Farmworker Legal Services. In the early 1980s, Payne and other faculty and students at Duke founded the Interns in Conscience project of the Hart Leadership Program, and groups of students went to southern Florida during summer breaks to work with agencies serving farmworkers.
In 1990, a grant from the U.S. Department of Education to the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke funded college student volunteers documenting the lives of migrant farmworker children. Fourteen Duke students in the summer of 1990 and eleven more in 1991 participated in the Center's Migrant Summer Program along with several University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill students. In 1992, students from Duke and UNC participated in a joint service-learning class about farmworker issues and the summer internship program.
Inspired by other activists, a group of students enlisted farmworker advocates, farmworkers, and community members to incorporate SAF as a nonprofit in 1992. Since 1992, SAF has directly impacted thousands of farmworkers, students and community members
As of 2007, the goals of SAF include:
To provide farmworkers and their families with greater access to existing resources through collaborations with farmworker advocacy organizations and community groups
To link student groups working with farmworkers in order to share their experiences and ideas
To increase the involvement of farmworkers in leadership and decision-making roles within SAF and to encourage such involvement within other organizations working on farmworker issues
To create a supportive environment for the efforts of farmworkers to improve their status in our society
To create internships and other projects that are mutually beneficially for students and farmworkers
To encourage student commitment to justice and social action
To increase interaction, communication and understanding among people of different backgrounds
To provide students from farmworker families with educational and career opportunities
To provide information on farmworker issues for students, faculty, religious organizations, advocacy organizations, and community groups
Access Restrictions
The Administrative Series and Student Projects Series are restricted: researchers must receive prior written authorization from SAF in order to access the material in these two series. All other series are unrestricted. Once authorization has been granted, SAF will contact the Rubenstein Library directly and provide name of researcher, dates of use, and which boxes may be accessed.
Original audiovisual media closed to use. Digital use copies are available upon request. As these require advance preparation, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Student Action With Farmworkers Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 2007, 2009, 2010, 2013, 2016, and 2018. Additional materials arrived from Joan Preiss in 2011.
Collection Overview
Founded in 1992 in Durham, North Carolina, Student Action with Farmworkers (SAF) is a non-profit organization whose mission is to bring students and farmworkers together to learn about each other's lives, share resources and skills, improve conditions for farmworkers, and build diverse coalitions working for social change. The SAF records comprise: correspondence; meeting agendas; student projects; reports, articles, and other publications; event files; teaching materials; photos; scrapbooks; ephemera; and other documentation of SAF's programs. Materials relate more widely to immigrant and migrant worker issues, service learning, labor organizing, and protests and boycotts across the U.S.
The largest series (63 boxes) contains hundreds of individual SAF student projects directed by college-age students and interns as well as farmworker and migrant youths. Materials also include administrative files, many of which house intern applications. Project files typically contain recorded interviews, often with transcripts; essays; notebooks; artwork; poetry; audio and video recordings; theater materials; and photographs in analaog and digital formats. Some photograph albums and collages are also found here. Most of the projects took place in North Carolina but also in South Carolina. Umbrella programs include Into the Fields (ITF) and Levante. Major themes involve worker education, housing, health, and pesticide safety; leadership development; and grassroots theater as a tool for teaching and activism. Materials are in English and Spanish. Many other materials on SAF projects are found in the Administrative Series.
The large Administrative Files Series contains organizational records created or compiled by SAF staff and are organized in subseries for SAF projects, fundraising, general administrative files, organizations, and resource files (articles, fliers, and other publications).
The Printed Material Series contains Student Action with Farmworkers publications, SAF press coverage, student papers and theses, some children's books, and farmworker-related reports, articles, newsletters, data sheets, resource directories, and alerts from around the world.
The Joan Preiss Papers Series contains records related to an activist and long-time collaborator of SAF. Comprises a variety of printed materials, primarily articles and newsletters, as well as correspondence, protest ephemera, promotional material for unions and activist organizations, meeting notes, student papers, and photographs. The materials relate to migrants and farmworkers both in North Carolina and throughout the United States.
Finally, the Ephemera and Artifacts Series contains items such as posters, t-shirts, stickers, and buttons related to Burger King, Subway, Gallo, and Mt. Olive boycotts and protests. Some materials relate to protests and boycotts in other regions such as Florida and Western states. Also contains SAF publicity ephemera, and props and other materials from the Levante activist theater group.
Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Related Materials
Related collection: Joan Preiss papers, 1970-2006, Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Agriculture -- North Carolina; Agricultural laborers -- Health; Agricultural laborers -- North Carolina; Children of migrant laborers; Documentary Photography -- North Carolina; Migrant agricultural laborers -- North Carolina; Migrant agricultural laborers -- Services for -- United States; Migrant workers -- North Carolina; Pesticides -- Health aspects -- United States; Student movements -- North Carolina; Student service -- United States; Theater -- Political aspects; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Color slides; CD-ROMs; Digital moving image formats; Digital images; DVDs; Electronic documents; Journals; Moving images; Negatives (photographs); Oral histories (document genre); Videocassettes; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Duke University -- Students -- Political activity; Student Action with Farmworkers (Organization)
- Administrative Files, 1992-2020; 1992-ongoing and undated; 50 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Access to this series is restricted to researchers who have received prior authorization from the donor. Please contact Research Services for further assistance.
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains administrative and subject files organized under the following subseries: Projects, Fundraising, General Administrative, Organizations, Resource Files, and Photographs and Scrapbooks.
  The General Administrative series houses administrative files which fall outside of the other categories: these include Board of Directors files, meeting minutes and agendas, finance and operations folders, events files, student and personnel policies, and outreach and correspondence files.
  The Resource Files series contains chiefly articles on a wide variety of topics related to farmworkers and migrant workers.
  Within subseries, groups and individual folders are organized alphabetically, with the exception of the Photos and Scrapbooks series, which is organized chronologically. Most titles were transcribed from the original folders; others have been devised by library staff.
  - Projects, 1998-2020; 1998-ongoing
    Contains files related to various SAF projects and initiatives as well as other organizations' projects which SAF contributed to. These include Farmworker Awareness Week, Sowing Seeds of Change, Adelante, Farmworker Advocacy Network, and SAF fellowships. Materials include manuals, correspondence, budgets, goals, meeting and committee notes, research, and publicity material
    - Project files, Adelante (Box 8)
    - Adelante website, 2014-2020; 2014-
    - Project files, Adelante, 2012-2013; 2 folders (Box 109)
      Scope and Contents
      Handouts, program models, prints
    - Project files, Adelante, 2013-2016; 8 folders (Box 117)
      Administrative files include meeting agendas and notes, communications training, retreat notes and agendas, assessments, program planning, and work plans for interns for the years 2013-2016. Programs mentioned revolve around youth organizing: Latino Student Success, Let's Learn NC, Encuentro, and Student Leadership Institutes, as well as parent and family advocacy and tuition equity.
    - Project files A-C (Box 1)
    - Project files C-F (Box 2)
    - Project files F (Box 3)
    - Bandana Project, 2009 (Box 95)
    - Project files, Farmworkers Action Network (FAN), 2010-2014; 17 folders (Box 117)
      Administrative files in the FAN group as a whole include: planning documents; meeting agendas and notes; Harvest of Dignity program records; DACA training; child labor and other data; assessments; accomplishment files; member and partner organization information. Major initiatives represented chiefly concern workers' safety, and include a poulty workers campaign and pesticide training, as well as consumer awareness outreach.
    - Project files, Farmworkers Action Network (FAN), 2014-2016; 35 folders 1 box (Box 118)
    - Farmworker Awareness Campaign, 2009 (Box 95)
    - Farmworker Awareness Campaign, 2010 (Box 95)
    - Farmworker Awareness Campaign, 2011 (Box 95)
    - Farmworker Awareness Week, 2011 (Box 95)
    - Farmworker Institute, 2008-2010 (Box 95)
    - Project files F-N (Box 4)
    - Project files N-S (Box 5)
    - North Carolina Farmworkers website, 2014-2020
    - Farmworker Advocacy Network website, 2014-2020; 2014-
    - Project files F-S, 2011-2014; 44 folders (Box 109)
      Farmers Advocacy Network: communications, leadership team, meeting minutes, retreats, ROOTS documents
      Students Organizing Schools: evaluation forms, orientation, retreats, work plans
    - Project files S, 1998-2014; 14 folders (Box 110)
      Students Organizing Schools: applications, manuals, orientation, program committees
      Sowing Seeds for Change: applications, community health project, symposia documents
    - Project files, SAF Student Organizing School and Leadership Institute (SOS, LLI), 2010-2016; 26 folders 1 box (Box 119)
      Files comprise Student Organizing School student applications, manuals and orientation materials, meetings (chiefly retreats), assessments, and materials on various program partners, especially Duke Engage and Oxfam.
    - Project files, Solidaridad Internship program, 2014-2015 and undated; 8 folders (Box 120)
      Files cover most aspects of the Solidaridad Internship, including orientations, manuals, meetings, work plans for interns, and program notes. Interns collaborated with SAF staff on Student Organizing School (SOS), Leadership Institute (LLI), Levante, and other programs, thus, materials on these programs are scattered throughout the files. The bulk of materials on these programs are found in their respective administrative groups under this same Projects subseries.
    - Project files S-U (Box 6)
    - Project files U-W (Box 7)
  - Fundraising Files, 1999-2016
    Contains files related to fundraising projects.
    - Fundraising files (Box 7)
    - Harvest of Women's Voices, SAF fundraiser [broadside], 1995 (Oversize-box 147)
    - Fundraising files, 2011-2012; 6 folders (Box 110)
      20th anniversary fundraising, online fundraising, grant application
    - Fundraising - SAF Alumni Program, 1999-2013; 11 folders (Box 120)
      Files in this group include SAF alumni lists, outreach, and surveys; they reflect efforts from 2000 onwards to cultivate long-lasting relationships with SAF alumni, for the purposes of fundraising and forming networks.
    - Fundraising - SAF Alumni Program, 2010-2014; 13 folders 1 box (Box 121)
    - Fundraising - SAF Alumni Program, 2013-2016; 5 folders (Box 122)
  - General Files, 1990-2020; 1990-ongoing
    Contains files related to general office management. Subgroups include records related to events, financial activities, staffing, and documentary award management.
    - Administrative files (Box 7)
    - Administrative files, 2011-2014; 66 folders (Box 108)
      Documents pertaining to: board meeting agendas, curriculum planning, exhibit materials, program committees, staff retreats, strategic planning
    - Administrative files, 2011-2014; 10 folders (Box 109)
      20th anniversary materials, university calendars, workstudy paperwork
    - Annual reports and planning, 2012-2017; 6 folders (Box 122)
    - Annual SAF report, SAF: The First Year, 1992-1993 (Box 122)
      Sixteen-page report includes SAF history, tracing the evolution of SAF from the 1970s; programs and services summaries; internships report; special events; fundraising breakdown; planning; and governance.
    - Awards, 2005, 2014-2017; 9 items (Box 122)
      Chiefly congratulatory letters from Senator David Price, Representative Butterfield, and Governor Cooper. Includes four items associated with the 2005 Eleanor Roosevelt Human Rights Award to SAF.
    - Board of Directors, 2013-2014; 1 folders (Box 122)
    - Board of Directors, 2014-2016 and undated; 4 folders (Box 123)
    - Cesar Chavez Day, 2012 (Box 95)
    - Communications and outreach, 2004-2009, 2010-2016 and undated; 10 folders (Box 123)
      Files relate to outreach planning and activities, media and press, the SAF website, and a mural. Includes a "No Sweatshops" action kit, circa 2004-2009, and some blank SAF greeting cards. Other files related to communications and outreach can be found throughout the collection, especially in the Administrative Series; many references to planning for outreach are found in meeting minutes.
    - Correspondence, 1990-1993 (Box 123)
      Chiefly letters from the SAF coordinator, Carolyn Corrie, to Robert Cole, to donors and partners in the new project, to board members, and to Duke University President Keith Brodie. The letters to Cole especially give insights into the early efforts to shape SAF's programs and mission.
    - Database, 2008-2009 (Box 95)
    - Database, 2009-2010 (Box 95)
    - Database, 2010-2011 (Box 95)
    - Documentary award files, 2012-2016; 5 folders (Box 124)
      Materials relate to the Petrow-Freeman Documentary Award, and include applications, correspondence, evaluations, meeting agendas, planning, timelimes, and notes on how to best accomplish documentary activities. Other documentary projects also include One Thing/Una Cosa (Summer 2016).
    - Duke Engage, 2010 (Box 95)
    - Duke Engage, 2010-2011 (Box 95)
    - Events, 1998-2013; 11 folders (Box 124)
      Files relate to various engagements, speaker requests, and events such as marches, conferences, exhibit openings, and presentations on a wide variety of topics. Includes materials on 20th anniversary events (2012).
    - Melinda and Laxmi anniversary parties, 2011 (Box 97)
    - Events, 2014-2016; 16 folders 1 box (Box 125)
      Materials concern speaker requests, presentations, and the SAF End-of-Summer celebration. Includes NC Farmworker Institute stakeholder session with the EPA. Also of note are 56 detailed farmworker surveys taken during a NC Farmworker Festival, 2014; questions focus on their methods of communication within the U.S., languages spoken other than Spanish (Mixtec, Nahuatal, Purépecha included among the answers), and what information they would be interested in receiving from SAF.
    - Financial, 1994-2004, 2012-2015 (Box 126)
      Receipts, 1994-2004, budget reports showing losses and gains, and sponsorships.
    - Images for fliers, undated (Box 95)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 98)
    - Operating procedures and personnel policies, 2008 Nov.-2009 Nov. (Box 98)
    - Original drawings, undated (Box 98)
    - RBMSCL/UA exhibit separation sheets, 2012 (Box 98)
    - Sowing Seeds for Change declines, 2011 (Box 98)
    - Stencils and artwork, undated (Box 98)
    - Student Action with Farmworkers staff FAC, 2011 (Box 98)
    - Student Action with Farmworkers Twitter, 2012-2020; 2012-
    - Student Action with Farmworkers website, 2011-2020; 2011-
    - SOS administrative files, 2010-2011, 9 folders (Box 98)
    - Staffing, 2011-2016; 14 folders (Box 126)
      Folders typically include staff meetings, staff retreats, and work-study applications. There are also a few recommendation files and a lobbying file. Other files related to staffing (correspondence, recommendations, events) can be found throughout the Administrative series, and in separate groupings such as Work-Study.
      Student administrative files associated with Into the Fields and other documentary projects are located in the Student Projects Series, though there may be some stray files in the larger Administrative Series.
    - Work-study, 2009-2010 (Box 98)
    - Work-study, 2010-2011 (Box 98)
  - Organizations, 1987-2016
    Contains files related to organizations that SAF has worked with or followed, such as colleges and non-profit organizations. College files include information on fellowships and student activism and contain materials such as flyers, booklets, and correspondence. Other organization files contain publications, newsletters, reports, and correspondence from advocacy organizations, governmental organizations, etc. related to farmworkers, labor, and latinos nationally and in North Carolina
    - College files A-D (Box 7)
    - College files D-Y (Box 9)
    - Organization files A (Box 9)
    - Organization files A-D (Box 10)
    - Organization files D-F (Box 11)
    - Organization files F (Box 12)
    - Organization files G-M (Box 13)
    - Organization files M-N (Box 14)
    - Organization files N-P (Box 15)
    - Organization files P-S (Box 16)
    - Organization files T-Y (Box 17)
    - Organization files A-U, 1987-2014; 24 folders (Box 110)
      Handouts, conference binders, meeting agendas
    - Organization files A-H, 1993-2012 and undated; 4 folders (Box 126)
      AFL-CIO, Duke Divinity, and Housing Development Corporation (2)
    - Organizations - H (Housing Development Corporation), 1981-2013; 11 folders (Box 127)
      Files relate to the founding and activities of the NC Council of Churches Housing Development Corporation, a coalition which includes Student Action with Farmworkers. Files contain HDC articles of incorporation, bylaws, meeting minutes, planning notes, and records of the HDC's Heifer Project and Farmworkers Garden Project.
    - Organization files H-Z, 1991-1995, 2013-2016; 14 folders (Box 128)
      Organizations include: Latino groups active in education and philanthropy; higher education partners such as NC State and UNC; St. Anthony Farmworkers' Association (1991-1992); and out-of-state projects such as Unidos (New Mexico) and Positive Action Committee Student Success program materials (Georgia). Meeting materials include a Youth Organizing Institute and Youth Power Conference in Durham, NC, and a Z. Smith Reynolds planning retreat on immigrant justice in NC.
  - Resource Files and Articles, 1994-2014
    Contains articles used in research and at conferences. Files and articles are organized in alphabetical order by subject or title. Topics include activism, health and safety, alcoholism, migrant labor, human trafficking, access to worker camps (information for interns and staff), and comprehensive indexes and listings for farmworker resources.
    - Conference articles (Box 17)
    - General articles, agriculture (Box 17)
    - General articles, agriculture-farmworkers (Box 18)
    - General articles, farmworkers-health (Box 19)
    - General articles, health-organizing (Box 20)
    - General articles, organizing-racism (Box 21)
    - Resource files, A-M, 1994-2013; 12 folders 1 box (Box 129)